George William Curtis Letters
George William Curtis Letters
1851-1892
Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.
89 items (SC)
Papers of the American critic, social commentator, essayist; Chiefly outgoing correspondence.
149356
Biographical History
George William Curtis (1824-1892) was an American critic, social commentator, and essayist.
Select Works
1851 Nile Notes of a Howadji
1852 The Howadji in Syria Lotus-Eating: A Summer Book
1853 The Potiphar Papers
1856 Prue and I Our Best Society
1861 Trumps. A Novel
1891 Washington Irving: A Sketch
1891-1894 From the Easy Chair, 3 volumes
1893 Other Essays from the Easy Chair
1894 Orations and Addresses of George William Curtis Literary and Social Essays
1896 Emerson Hawthorne Longfellow
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George William Curtis Letters are a collection of chiefly outgoing Correspondence which illuminate the journalism career, political activities, and personal life of this 19th century American social commentator and orator. As editor of "The Easy Chair," a feature which appeared in Harper's Monthly, Curtis's widely-read opinions generated interest in him as a speaker, and a number of letters concern invitations to address various political organizations and educational institutions (Bond, Lee, Partington, Prince). Also among the letters are several responses to social invitations (Croffut, Graham, Hart, Tenney, Wharton), and a number of more personal letters (Dwight, Downing, Fields, Robbins, Taylor) which concern social engagements, typical among them is this to Eastman: "I cannot tell you how fresh and beautiful the little excursion was - nor how much I owe you - euchre included."
While the personal letters (Lossing, Putnam, Stoddard) reveal much of the wit and warmth of Curtis the journalist and literary critic, there are also a number of letters which reflect on beliefs and opinions of this political activist (Moffat, Pruyn, Ranney, Pierrepont). Responding to his nomination by acclamation for Secretary of State of New York at the Republican convention, Curtis wrote to Judge Edwards Pierrepont ( 1 Oct 1869 ):
Certainly one of the most agreeable events in a man's life must be his summons to an honorable public position by the spontaneous and unanimous voice of a multitude of his fellow citizens personally unknown to him; and certainly he must feel very grateful to the friend who was the immediate cause of that expression of preference. You must know, therefore, before I say it, how sincerely I thank you for naming me in the Convention and how truly sorry I am that I could not, with an honorable regard for my present duties and engagements, even permit myself to think of accepting.
I hope meanwhile, to be of more actual service both to the state and to the country in an unofficial post.
Although active in Republican Party politics, Curtis rejected the choice of James G. Blaine for the American presidency and urged the election of Grover Cleveland, becoming the most influential of the Independents in national affairs. In a letter of 14 Nov 1884, Curtis explains:
If support of a candidate who is believed to be dishonest or of a measure which is thought to be injurious to the public welfare, be compatible with Republicanism, no self respecting man can be a Republican.
And in a letter addressed to Henry S. Ranney and others, Curtis outlines his personal view of the role of political parties ( 30 Oct 1829 ):
You hold that the first duty of an American citizen is to his country; and while we all agree that under our political system the country is to be served through party organization, you assert the great conservative truth that organization can be kept faithful to its purpose only by the individual independence of its members. Undoubtedly the party majority must rule but the only way to compel it to rule rightly is to refuse obedience to its recommendations when they cannot be obeyed without sacrifice of principle.
Offering some advice to an aspiring social activist; Curtis advises C. W. Stickney ( 15 Feb 1870 ):
I should beg you to think a little of the manner of your action, whether speaking or writing or advocating this or that special measure - but everything of great result, and of the carefulness, the conscience, the training, the knowledge, which are essential to success in every form. If you fit your heart upon the pen as your weapon, - it may deceive you. If upon the tongue, - it may disappoint you. But everywhere and everyhow as opportunity offers, to speak or to write or to do, for whatever is best and generous & manly, that is really to live, and not to do it is to die.
The Subject Files series contains a single photograph.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into two series: Subject Files and Correspondence. The correspondence is arranged chronologically; there is a Selected Index to Correspondence located at the end of the finding aid.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Bond, William.; Bourne, Wm. Oland (William Oland), 1819-1901.; Cotting, Benjamin Eddy, 1812-1897.; Croffut, William Augustus.; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.; Dwight, John Sullivan, 1813-1893.; Fields, James Thomas, 1817-1881.; Lanman, Charles, 1819-1895.; Lossing, Helen (Mrs. Benson); Moffat, Reuben Burnham, 1861-; Pierrepont, Edwards, 1817-1892.; Pruyn, John VanSchaick Lansing, 1811-1877.; Putnam, George Palmer, 1814-1872.; Ranney, Henry S.; Stickney, C. W.; Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903.; Taylor, Bayard, 1825-1878.; Tenney, William Jewett.; Ward, William Hayes.; White, Francis Wayland.; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892.; Republican Party (N.Y.); American literature -- 19th century.; Authors, American.; Journalists -- Political activity.; Journalists -- United States.; New England -- Intellectual life.; New England -- Social life and customs.; New York (State) -- Politics and government.; Letters (correspondence); Authors.; Journalists.; Journalism
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Subject Files
  - Photograph, undated (Sc 71)
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing, 1851-1855; 4 letters (Sc 71)
  - Outgoing, 1856-1859; 7 letters (Sc 71)
  - Outgoing, 1860-1865; 10 letters (Sc 71)
  - Outgoing, 1866-1869; 11 letters (Sc 71)
  - Outgoing, 1870-1874; includes 1 fragment of incoming letter; 10 letters; 1 fragment (Sc 71)
  - Outgoing, 1875-1879; 10 letters (Sc 71)
  - Outgoing, 1880-1884; 12 letters (Sc 71)
  - Outgoing, 1885-1889; 11 letters (Sc 71)
  - Outgoing, 1890-1892; 12 letters (Sc 71)
Selected Index to Correspondence
Black 1 Apr 1862
Bonaparte, Mr. 3 Jan 1889
Bond, William 9 Sep 1857
Bourne, William Oland 12 Feb 1866 13 Mar 1866 16 Apr 1874
Chadwick 20 Apr 1875
Collins, Mr. 16 Dec 1857
Cotting, Benjamin Eddy 19 Jan 1856
Croffut, William Augustus 28 Feb 1867
Downing, Mrs. 28 Jan 1855
Dwight, John Sullivan 12 Aug 1851
Eastman 3 Aug 1862
Eleanor 1 Nov 1875
Fields, James Thomas 16 Mar 1857 7 Oct 1861 10 Dec 1872
Francis, David G. 26 Dec 1883
Gilder, Mr. 17 May 1890
Graham, Mr. 10 Dec 1865 23 Dec 1865
Hart, Dr. 1 Jun 1870 25 Nov 1871
Horatio 8 Dec 1878
Huntington, D 21 Nov 1879 2 Dec 1879
Ireland, Mr. 18 Apr 1879
Lanman, Charles 24 Jan 1878
Lee, Mr. 18 Dec 1859
Lossing, Helen (Mrs. Benson) 8 Apr 1866
Mackaye, Mrs. 11 Jul 1888
Mayer, Mr. 23 Mar 1857
Moffat, Reuben Burnham 22 Nov 1884
Osgood, J. R. & Co. 20 Jan 1875
Partington, Mr. 15 Apr 1888 1 Jun 1889 5 Feb 1890 2 Jun 1890 18 Aug 1891 18 Feb 1892 15 Jun 1892
Pierrepont, Edwards 1 Oct 1869
Prince, Mr. 20 Jan 1865
Pruyn, Anna Parker 12 Jun 1890
Pruyn, John VanSchaick Lansing 25 Sep 1867
Putnam, George Palmer 2 Dec 1863 9 Jan 1869
Ranney, Henry S. 30 Oct 1879
Richards, Mr. 5 May 1890
Richelson, Mr. 21 Oct 1874
Robbins, Mr. 31 Dec 1860
Sargent, Mr. 26 Apr 1866
Sheldon, Mr. 20 Oct 1888
Sherwood, Mr. 12 Jun 1885
Smith, Mr. 23 Oct 1872
Stickney, C. W. 15 Feb 1870
Stoddard, Richard Henry 22 Oct 1859
Taylor, Bayard 25 Feb 1865
Tenney, William Jewett 22 Sep 1867
Ward, William Hayes 14 Nov 1881
Wharton, Mr. 2 Oct 1885
White, Francis Wayland 22 Jan 1855
Whittier, John Greenleaf 20 Jan 1884
Wilstach, Mr. 27 Dec 1881
Wiman, Mr. 12 May 1890